<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sions enemy discovered, or the worker of iniquity rebuked and innocency cleared in a reply to seven sheets of paper published by Jonathan Johnson of Lincoln, and by him entituled, The Quaker quashed, and his quarrel queld, &amp;c.</title>
            <author>Mason, Martin, fl. 1650-1676.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52181</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M933A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221792</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833049</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833049</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37524</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52181)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37524)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2190:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sions enemy discovered, or the worker of iniquity rebuked and innocency cleared in a reply to seven sheets of paper published by Jonathan Johnson of Lincoln, and by him entituled, The Quaker quashed, and his quarrel queld, &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Mason, Martin, fl. 1650-1676.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Written by a lover of your souls Martin Mason.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Dated at end: Lincoln. 28. day 5. Moneth 1659.; place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>In response to Johnson, Jonathan.  The Quaker quasht and his quarrel quelled.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Friends' House Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Johnson, Jonathan, --  of Suffolk? --  Quaker quasht and his quarrel quelled --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37524:1"/>
            <head>SIONS <hi>ENEMY DISCOVERED, OR</hi> The Worker of iniquity rebuked <hi>AND</hi> INNOCENCY CLEARED, In a Reply to ſeven ſheets of Paper Publiſhed by <hi>Jona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than Johnſon</hi> of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> and by him Entituled, <hi>The Quaker quaſht, and his quarrel queld, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>JONATHAN,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I ſhall not here take notice of every polluted ſtream coming from the Fountain of thy corrupt heart, which in thy papers thou haſt pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed: Thou runs on at a high rate, as if there were not a righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God that takes notice of, and regiſters all the wrongs done unto his people; abide thou no longer in the dark habitation of the Hipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, for though thou haſt told the World thou expectedſt my ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of my evil in writing againſt thee, as if that were the cauſe thou kept thy papers almoſt theſe two years by thee, yet thy fig leaves cannot cover thee, the light of <hi>Iſrael</hi> doth diſcern thee, and thou ſhalt one day know they were ſober lines wch then were ſent thee, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n thou writſt laſt to me, and happy hadſt thou been, if thou wouldſt have been warned by me. Thou tells me (page 1) <hi>That I Bragadot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>-like, ſaid, I will not give one inch of ground, or turn my back off the uncircumciſed Philiſtine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let the ſober Reader peruſe my book and he may ſee that (in anſwer to thy charge of the weakneſſe and diſarmed condition of thoſe I am en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camped with, and that our weapon is but a bull ruſh.</p>
            <p>I told thee, <hi>It was not th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> nor thy Fathers legion, could make one Souldier in the camp of the Lord give one inch of ground or turn his back off the uncircumciſed Philiſtine.</hi> Judge honeſt Reader; hath not the wicked one wreſted my words? but when will he learn to ſpeak truth? ſay <hi>Jonathan,</hi> doſt thou not ſee thy bold preſumption that wouldſt have thy engagement to be compared with <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See his book p. 1.2.</note> and my words with <hi>Goltan;</hi> Come down ſon of ambition, <hi>David</hi> was a man after Gods own heart, but thy hearr is not circumciſed, therefore bluſh and be aſhamed.</p>
            <p>I asked thee this queſtion, <hi>Hath every one that cometh into the world heard and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:37524:2"/>read the preaching of Chriſt and his Apoſtles as they are tranſcribed in the Bible?</hi> to which thou didſt poſitively anſwer, <hi>They have all heard,</hi> and yet like a ſon of impudence in thy book thou denieſt it; and chargeſt me, <hi>that I have dealt falſly with thy anſwer;</hi> To which I reply, the Lord of heaven and earth be judge betwixt us, whether them were thy words, or nay. And becauſe thou art ſo confident in thy darkneſſe, I tell thee, millions of men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men may witneſſe againſt thee, that they never read the preachings of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, as they are tranſcribed in the Bible. To my other queſtion, <hi>How is the Goſpel preached to every creature under heaven which is the power of God, if not by that principle of light in the conſcience? In thy book thou anſwereſt thus, In the preaching of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, which worketh the principle of light in the conſcience, and whatſoever is not enlightned from thence tis darkneſſe, and not light:</hi> Be not theſe thy own words? Art thou an elder <hi>Jonathan,</hi> or head or leader of a ſeparated people, and ſo ſottiſh to make the letter the author of the light of Chriſt in the conſcience, (which was before the letter was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven forth?) as if a man gave being to his maker; Sure if thy Church were in God the Father of lights, they would ſee thy nakedneſſe and be aſhamed: Thou multiplyeſt many words about <hi>the ſound of accuſing or excuſing in all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences,</hi> I am ſatisfied that thou diddſt confeſs, that the ſound of accuſing or excuſing is in all conſciences, and knowes it is accuſing not excuſing, thee in thy conſcience, for ſeveral ſins thou commits againſt it: And thy dark aſſertion, <hi>that it comes only by the hearing of faith preached by the Apoſtles,</hi> doth more manifeſt thy miſerable nakedneſs, and thy groſſe ignorance of Chriſt the power of God, and of his kingdome where it is, and what.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">pag. 5.</note>Thou confeſſeth, <hi>there was a principle of light in the people before</hi> Moſes <hi>writ the letter,</hi> and ſubtilly ſpeaks of Chriſts ſending the people to <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets to hear them.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 5 46.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I grant thee, he did ſo, and I give thee this reaſon, recorded in ſcripture, <hi>Had they believed</hi> Moſes, <hi>they would have believed Chriſt, for</hi> Moſes <hi>writ of Chriſt.</hi> So now we deſire people would wiſely read and ſearch the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, for they do teſtifie of the light of Chriſt in the conſcience, but many read them fooliſhly as thou doſt, and think in them to have eternal life. but come not to be guided by the light of Chriſt in the conſcience, and ſo fall ſhort of eternal life. Charge me no more, with uſeing this phraſe, <hi>the light of conſcience,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.19</note> for thou never receivedſt it from me: Conſcience is dark un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till it be awaked, untill the light of Chriſt in the conſcience, ariſe and ſhine in the heart, nor do the children of the day, or true Miniſters of the light direct the hearts or conſciences of the people to any other thing then <hi>that ſure word of Propheſie,</hi> the light of Chriſt in the conſcience, (who is the ſeed of the woman, the word of God) though ſuch as thou, believes not in it, and thats the reaſon you are not ſaved by it, ſo ſin hath dominion over you,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16</note> becauſe you believe not in the light of Chriſt in the conſcience, <hi>which is the power of God unto ſalvation, to all that believe therein,</hi> and while thy car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal minde is gazing after a Chriſt without as the Jewes did, thou art not like to find him within thee, but as a condemner of thee; and know this alſo I am not aſhamed to aſſirme unto thee, that the grace of God which brings ſalvation hath appeared unto all men, though all do not receive ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation by it, becauſe they believe not in it, no more doſt thou, while thus thou perſecutes it, and ſmites the innocent Lambs with the fiſt of wickedneſſe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.4.</note> Wherefore haſt thou dealt thus unworthyly with me in thy ninth p. <hi>with thy ſave only, &amp;c,</hi> thus boldly to aſſirme that I granted to thee, <hi>that the light in the conſcience
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:37524:2"/>comes by the hearing of faith preached by the Apoſtles,</hi> as if the letter were the author of the light. How haſt thou polluted thy garment with a lye? but no better dealing do I look for, from thee, while blindneſſe of heart thus reſts upon thee: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph,</hi> 4.18:</note>I own that which <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> preached from, to be the ſpirit of the living God, and what they ſpake from the mouth of the Lord, I own to be the winde or words of the Lord: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Io.</hi> 8.12. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.13.</note>But ſtill afirming, as as I did before, that Chriſt (the light of the world) is the word of God from whom the words proceeded, by whom the world was made, and ſo the letter muſt give place to the ſpirit, the ſervant is not greater then his maſter, the light was the life, and being of all the true Prophets and Apoſtles, who ſpake and writ the ſcriptures, and they preached the word to be nigh even in the heart, and laboured to turn men from darkeneſſe unto light, and from the power of Satan unto God. <hi>Deu.</hi> 30.14. <hi>Ro.</hi> 10.8.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Io.</hi> 10. <hi>Io.</hi> 13.16. <hi>Act.</hi> 17.28</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That which gave forth the leaves, ſaid I.</hi> I own, and thou caſts this upon me; The printer gave forth the leaves, but I tell thee now as I did before, it was the ſpirit of God, that gave the ſcriptures, and its that <hi>I</hi> own, and not the Printer as the author of them; does the printer give or ſell them? But <note place="margin">Pro. 27.22.</note>
               <hi>bray a fool in a morter, yet his folly will not leave him:</hi> Thy ſcornfull upbrayd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me, with a miſtake in the title page of my former book, <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.10.</note>
               <hi>as if I had pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed my ſelfe a Miniſter of the Goſpel,</hi> does not become thee, nor (things well weighed) do I deſerve it from thee. <hi>By the Grace of God I am What I am,</hi> though no Miniſter (in that ſence thy envious mind receives it) yet a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant in my meaſure, not of the letter but of the everlaſting Goſpel: And I want not witneſs within nor without, that I did neither then, nor doeth now ſo appropriate that title to my ſelf, but intended it to one, who then did well deſerve it. And had not the printer begun a new line where he ſhould not, thou hadſt wanted this ſtone to have flung at the innocent. Thou buſieſt thy ſelfe with babling of <hi>the baptiſm of repentance,</hi> and ſpends many words to no purpoſe about it; were it leſſe in thy tongue and better witneſſed in thy heart, it were better for thee The <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.14</note>
               <hi>light of conſcience</hi> as thou calls it, thou haſt again in thy mouth, happy were it for thee if thy conſcience were made clean with the blood of the lamb, and purified with the light that is in it, which light once under thy own hand thou didſt own to be the in-let to the ſpirit of promiſe, though n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w with impudence thou denyes it. And if ever thou own the truth as it is in Jeſus, this thou wilt ſee, and confeſſe with ſorrow many things which are now denyed by thee; till thou, ſilence thou child of ignorance, and boaſt not above thy meaſure, and lean no longer on a reed of <hi>Egypt,</hi> while the baptiſm of repentance from dead works is not wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed by thee. And tel the world no longer, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.13.</note>
               <hi>that we are denyers of that Chriſt Jeſus who ſuffered at Jeruſalem,</hi> for his ſufferings we own, who wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed a good confeſſion before <hi>Pontius Pilate;</hi> but whats his ſufferings unto thee whilſt thou art an enemy to that Righteou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Seed within thee, which is a continual remembrancer unto thee, and reprover of thee. As for thy aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſions unworthily caſt upon me, as if <hi>I had denyed his ſufferings without the gues at Jeruſalem,</hi> who ever reads my book with a ſingle eye, may ſee thee ſlandring of the innocent and thats not the worke of a ſervant of Jeſus Chriſt as thou haſt publiſhed thy ſelfe to be. Thy ſhunting and rayling terms to my queries mentioned in thy 17. page, is no good anſwer, it may be if thou liveſt two yeares longer, thou maiſt more wiſely conſider of them; In the meane time let the honeſt reader obſerve, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> although thou thus un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:37524:3"/>
               <note place="margin">They who live in ſin are ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to ſin and ſo out of the faith which puri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fies the heart and givs victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry over ſin, and there<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore ſuch while they are ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to ſin are not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed from their ſins.</note>reproaches me as if I denyed the ſufferings of Chriſt; noe ground for this thou haſt I know of; tis true, I ſaid thou and they who feed your ſelves with the meer frothy verbal faith in the ſufferings of the man Chriſt Jeſus at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and yet wallow in your wickedneſſe, are not ſaved or redeemed from your ſins. Now whether this be a denyal of Chriſts ſufferings or not, let the righteous witneſſe in all conſciences, judge between us: Beſides I told thee then, no other Jeſus did I own but that lamb of God who was ſlain from the beginning of the world, and that the fulneſſe of the Godhead dwels bodily in him, he was apointed above his fellowes, and yet the ſon of impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence tels people <hi>I deny him,</hi> but my witneſſe within me doth herein juſtifie me, and he is greater then my falſe accuſer without me: To what end is all thy loud outcries againſt the harmleſſe children of the light, ranking them among the worſt of men, and rendring them as odious to the world, with thy reproachful pen, as thy wrathful heart could invent, if not to ſharpen the edge of authority againſt them; but the perſecuting ſpirit is felt and fathomed, and its reward will not be wanting. I do not deny but the Apoſtles preacht all one Chriſt, and affirme that there is a witneſſe for God in all, though all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him not, no more doſt thou: he came to his own, and his own received him not, he that hath eares to hear let him hear; and it was Chriſt who preached in <hi>Paul</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles, and I tell thee <hi>Jonathan</hi> there are millions of men and women now on earth who never heard of the ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of Chriſt without the gates at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and yet the witneſſe of God is within them, and is calling them to come unto the Lord, that they may have life;<note place="margin">3 Col. 11.</note> and that is his voyce which reproves for ſin in the gate, though thou and thy generation trample on him and reject him; there is no room for him in the Inne, the manger muſt contain him; and ſo the pearle of great price is ſet at nought by the wiſe and prudent of the world.<note place="margin">Luke 2.7.</note> Thou ſpendeſt much paper in pleading for thy idol, to wit, <hi>outward water;</hi> and no other baptiſm I am bold to ſay knows thou, but that which never waſhed thee from thy ſins, thou art not come to the bridling of the tongue, ſo all thy religion is vain; <hi>Iohns</hi> Baptiſm I anſwer thee, was from <hi>God,</hi> it had its root and rife from him, and in its time and place was ſerviceable, but it ſhal have its end, he muſt increaſe ſaith <hi>Iohn,</hi> but I muſt decreaſe, ſpake he this of his perſon or of his miniſtration? let the voice of truth give anſwer to me; not do I deny but that the Apoſtles in honour to <hi>Iohns</hi> miniſtry made uſe of <hi>Iohns</hi> Baptiſm, by permiſſion, I ſay, and therein I do not judg them; &amp; prove thou if thou canſt, that it was by precept or command from Chriſt. But all thy twiſting and twining cannot do it. I tell thee once more, the light of Chriſt was in the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> and ſhined in their hearts, before their converſion to the Son of God, <hi>Paul</hi> preached the light unto them or directed them to the ſame principle of light within them; light ſhines in darkneſſe, though darkneſſe comprehends it not: The true light was within them, though not a Saviour to them, becauſe they believed not in it, nor was obedient to it. It was a condemning voice to them, as it is to thee and ſo before they believed in it, they were without God in the World, and ſo art thou. Be not angry if I tell thee, <hi>Jonathan,</hi> that Gods faithful witneſs now ſuffers within thee, thy works of iniquity wound the righteous ſoul within thee, with them he is preſſed as a cart with ſheavs; he is a man of ſorrows and ſuffers within thee, the juſt for the unjuſt; he is in the grave and not riſen in thee, &amp; did he not ſuffer for thee and within thee, thou ſhouldeſt ſoon ſeel that conſuming fire which is not to be quenched; And as for my charging thee <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:37524:3"/>thou ſaid <hi>I killed the ſcriptures,</hi> I tell thee <hi>Jonathan</hi> thou uſedſt theſe words to me, what light according to the word of God is in thee, to crucifie the Son of God again, and kill his preaching; Anſwer me plainly <hi>Jonathan,</hi> doſt thou not own the ſcriptures to be Chriſts preaching? then wherein have I wron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged thee? and now let him who is found with a lye in his mouth, waſh and be clean.<note place="margin">2 Ki. 5.13</note>
            </p>
            <p>Whether thou didſt call the ſcriptures <hi>dead letter</hi> or no, I ſhall leave the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber minded reader to judge, when I come to anſwer the 37 and 38 pages till then I ſpare thee, in the mean time I ſee thou wouldeſt fain ſhuffle off the words which I delivered concerning thee, in relation to thoſe called Dippers: peruſe thy paper and try if thoſe be not the words thou writſt unto me. <hi>viz. thou art forced to run for ſhelter and defence to thoſe thou accounts thy ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, thoſe who knows no other burial with Chriſt, but burial in water, and with them tells me of ſprinkling with water:</hi> but I tell thee, theſe chief Princes of <hi>Meſhech</hi> &amp; <hi>Tuball</hi> will be all found together to band themſelves againſt the peaceable ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation and dwelling of the Saints? theſe are thy own words <hi>Jonathan,</hi> though in thy fooliſh cover, thy wiſdome is confounded, which would have the world believe that theſe words of thine were applyed to me, and my gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration; but tell me, and let the voice of truth anſwer me, doſt thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve I account my own generation to be my enemies? I know they are the generation of the juſt which I do own, who know a better burial with Chriſt then burial in outward water, ſo I appeal with boldneſſe to the witneſſe of God in thy own conſcience; whether I had not good cauſe to conclude as I did concerning thee in this particular, and let the honeſt hearted reader, who reads with an impartial eye, judge if thou haſt not ſinned againſt thy own ſoul in this foul and fooliſh ſhufling.</p>
            <p>In my reply to the ſixt poſition, I uſed theſe words, (which thou very dceitſully haſt wreſted <hi>Is thy ſprinkling with water the baptiſm of Chriſt Jeſus yea or nay? And did the Lord command that to his diſciples, yea, or nay? And does the Lord require it of his people to this day? Now in thy letter thou ſaiſt, I bid thee prove whether Chriſt commanded baptiſme to his diſciples yea or nay? And did the Lord require it of his people to this day. I</hi> ſay, whether thy dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling thus deceitfully with my words be not a lye, and whether this decipt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full lye be not abominable, and whether nonſence be not lapt up in this lye or no, let the diſcreet reader judge between us. And what though <hi>I</hi> told thee, <hi>that I did never read nor know of one that pretends to more piety then thou doſt, that ever excelled or equalled thee in the deviliſh art of lying?</hi> Lying is his worke who abode not in the truth, and in that work thou art found, then what wrong have <hi>I</hi> done thee? <hi>I</hi> alſo told thee that a <hi>Notable</hi> ſervant thou wert to thy maſter, but <hi>I</hi> did not call thee <hi>Noble,</hi> for then <hi>I</hi> had wronged thee. And as for my words, <hi>That I would peruſe thoſe places thy Father ſent thee with, to fight for his Kingdome. I</hi> ſtill own them and thy works of iniquity makes it manyfeſt thou art not doing the will or worke of the living God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he is none of thy father, while the innocent ones thou ſlandreſt; tis the lying God thou ſerveſt, and he for his own ends makes uſe of ſcripture, to war againſt that ſpirit of truth, which gave forth ſcripture, and this the ſcriptures teſtifie, <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.6. Thou ſpends three or four ſides pleading for outward wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? <hi>I</hi> ſhall not follow thee in all thy crooked windings., but this <hi>I</hi> ſay ſtill, not thou, nor all thy generation, can by clear ſcripture prove: convince me <hi>that Chriſt gave an expreſſe command to any of his diſciples to baptize with outward water;</hi> So that though they in their chriſtian liberty did uſe it, wherein <hi>I</hi> do
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37524:4"/>not judge them, yet do <hi>I</hi> not juſtifie thee &amp; thy generation in your ſprinkling. <hi>I</hi> told thee ſome uſed circumciſion in the fleſh as well as baptiſing with out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward water, and <hi>I</hi> asked thee if their authority were not of an equal <hi>parity,</hi> though the printer miſtakeing, put an U for an <hi>A,</hi> but what if <hi>I</hi> had ſaid <hi>purity</hi> both by permiſſion, not by precept, and let mee aske thee and thy generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this queſtion, whether the commiſſion which Chriſt gave to his diſciples in Mat. 28. 19, 20. be not the ſame which <hi>paul</hi> received of him, or was his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion ſhort or contrary unto theirs? anſwer plainly; for <hi>Paul</hi> tells us plainly, he was not ſent to baptize but to preach the Goſple.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> told the people, <hi>in him, that is in his fleſh dwelt no good thing,</hi> doth he not explain his own words? <hi>when we were in the fleſh</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the motions of ſin did worke in our members to bring forth fruit unto death,</hi> obſerve this, He was not a chriſtian when ſuch fruites were brought forth; and are not ſuch fruits ſtill brought forth in thee? <hi>Paul</hi> then ſpake of a time paſt, but now ſaith he, <note place="margin">The let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter killeth</note>
               <hi>we are delivered from the Law that we ſhould ſerve in newneſſe of ſpirit, not in the oldneſſe of the letter</hi> (loe he calls ſcriptures the letter, and are they not ſo?) <hi>they that are in the fleſh cannot pleaſe God,</hi> Rom. 8.8, 9. <hi>but ye are not in the fleſh</hi> (yet they were alive upon earth) <hi>but in the ſpirit;</hi> and <hi>I</hi> tell thee <hi>Paul</hi> was filled with the holy Ghoſt, and he ſpake wiſdome amongſt them that were perfect, and what <hi>I</hi> ſent thee, as to perfection, does ſtand over thee: But why doſt thou tell me, <note place="margin">76 Pſ. 4.</note>
               <hi>that I ſtrive to get ſhut of the ſcriptures, and that their witneſs does torment me?</hi> theſe two lyes lye near one an other; and know thou O man the ſcriptures teſtimony is for me, and not againſt the truth which I hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth, viz. <hi>That the light of Chriſt in the conſcience is more glorious and excellent then the letter,</hi> and all thy babbling againſt perfection, is palpable contradiction to the doctrine of the Son of God, by him and his Apoſtles left upon record in ſcriptures: Thou art forced to confeſſe, <hi>That Abraham and the reſt of the holy men of God had the ſpirit of truth within them before the Law written by Moſes,</hi> And is not the Lord as good, as gratious now, as ever to his people? I tell thee he is now in the midſt of his people, and thouſands witneſſe his kingdome come and the King of Sion ſitting upon his throne in the hearts and conſciences of his people, though in thy dark mind thou wouldeſt exclude him, and confine or limit him above the ſtarrs; Chriſt when he was in that prepared body upon earth, was converſant with the Apoſtles, <note place="margin">i Pe. 3 19 <hi>Io.</hi> 5.25</note>
               <hi>and preached to the ſpirits in priſon, and the dead that did hear the voice of the ſon of God, did live;</hi> go learn what that meanes, and prove if thou canſt by Scripture that the ſpirit of truth is recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the letter, or by believing that to be the power of God unto ſalvation.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">pag. 33.</note>Thou babbleſt of one <hi>Henry Nicholas,</hi> and pours out the dregs of thy wrath even ſuch bitter foame as thy veſſel is filled with againſt the innocent lambs, who deny not, <hi>but do receive ſalvation from the ſame Chriſt that ſuffered without the gates at Jeruſalem;</hi> Therefore ſilence thou deceitful tongue, for tis thy ſelf and thy generation, who though in words you confeſs him (as the Pope does) yet by your works of iniquity you deny him, crying loe here, and loe there, but the ſaints know their ſaviour near them, he is within them, in their own boſomes, though fools boaſt of they know not what. Hadſt thou never read or heard of Scriptures, thou hadſt never known there is a Chriſt, or that the bodies of his people are his temple. By thy pleading againſt the Saints judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I may judge what thou art; ſhall not, and do not the ſaints judge the world? Is not thy heart in the world and worldly loſts and vanities? yea ſurely, and the judgements of the Son of God whom now thou perſecuteſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:37524:4"/>in his Saints, thou ſhalt find and feel, if at this repoof thou turneſt not.</p>
            <p>In thy 34. and 35. pages, thou ſaies, <hi>Thou judges me not, and askes where thou haſt judged the people called Dippers, &amp;c.</hi> To which I anſwer, if thou doſt not judge me, what meanes all thy foule mouthed language in theſe, and thy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer papers againſt me, but I know him who thus judges me, his name is the falſe accuſer of the brethren, and as for thoſe called Dippers, whether thou haſt not judged them or no, I appeale to the righteous witneſſe in thine, and their conſciences.</p>
            <p>In thy 36 page thou ſpeakeſt thou knoweſt not what, <hi>of the ſpirit that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnes to God that gave it,</hi> I tell thee that ſpirit which invents and loves a lye is for the lake: And tis that ſpirit which loves no iniquity that goes to God, and it was that ſpirit of truth in the Apoſtles which loved not a lye, that preached Chriſt and did worke miracles, which ſpirit they never received by reading <hi>Moſes</hi> or the Prophets. And as for the <hi>wolfe that would worry the weak,</hi> (mentioned in thy 37 page) he lodgeth near thee, he is within thee, but the pit is his portion.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe in thy 37 and 38 ſides, thou haſt dealt ſo deceitfully, miſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting thy own argument, and then putting a deceitfull cover upon it, I ſhall here lay down thy own words, and then take off thy polluted varniſh. This is thy argument; <hi>He that deſires to be tryed by the true touch-ſtone, the infalible Rule, the living principle of God, the light of Chriſt in the Saints conſciences, the ſpirit of truth, and would not be tryed by the dead letter, his ſpirit is of God, he is guided by the ſpirit of promiſe,</hi> but <hi>Jonathan Iohnſon</hi> deſires to be tryed as above ſaid, and not by the dead letter, therefore his ſpirit is of God, he's guided by the ſpirit of promiſe.</p>
            <p>Are not theſe thy own words? Then wherein have I wronged thee? but hath not the Lord herein confounded thy wiſdome, and ſuffered thee to utter words thou wouldeſt not, and now to ſave thy head thou runs to inventions and ſaies by <hi>dead letter</hi> thou meaneſt <hi>the Quakers books, the writings of</hi> M M. <hi>and his fellowes.</hi> Ah <hi>Jonathan</hi> this mantle doth not cover thee, this polluted gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will not ſhelter thee, tell me <hi>Jonathan,</hi> and <hi>I</hi> charge thee by the Lord thou let the voice of truth anſwer me, was not this the ground of that and other arguments, whether the Scriptures or the ſpirit were the rule; not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>writings</hi> of thoſe whom thou cals <hi>Quakers,</hi> or the ſpirit were the rule, were ever ſuch words exchanged between us? O that thy eye were opened, that thou mighteſt ſee thy nakedneſſe, and be aſhamed.</p>
            <p>In the 40 page thou tells the people, whoſoever reads and <hi>obſerve me, will ſee my deſire to ſet up my ſelſe as a wiſe maſter builder,</hi> but let the diſcreet rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſee what ground <hi>I</hi> gave thee, to write ſo ſcornfully concerning me, the words in my book are theſe, <hi>according to the grace of God that is given unto me as a wiſe maſter builder I have laid the foundation, ſaith</hi> Paul, 1 Cor. 3.10. He built upon the rock<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> now I ſay upon the ſame rock (which was Chriſt the light whom <hi>Paul</hi> preached) my building is, and upon no other, which was in <hi>Paul'</hi> before he preached him, and ſo by the ſame grace, <hi>I am what I am,</hi> but who can eſcape the reproach of the envyous?</p>
            <p>In thy 41 page ſpeaking as to ſome words <hi>I</hi> uſed in my book, <hi>That which lay dead, did at the hearing of the voice of the Son of God live,</hi> Thou anſwers, <hi>That which here lay dead is,</hi> but <hi>I</hi> never told thee ſo, <hi>that which before I called the Chriſt in all the Royal ſeed, the unction, the Lord of glory crucified in them, ſo that by my doctrine</hi> (ſaiſt thou) <hi>The Royal ſeed, the unction, the Lord of glory and Chriſt in all
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:37524:5"/>lay dead, till it did at the hearing of the voice of the Son of God, live, and then aske<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> what greater confuſed nonſence can be delivered, then to ſay Chriſt the Son of God lyeth dead, until he hear the voice of Chriſt the Son of God and live, can ſuch bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling be without blaſphemy?</hi> ſaiſt thou,</p>
            <p>To all which <hi>Jonathan, I</hi> reply, let the honeſt hearted reader peruſe my book, <hi>and Wiſdome will be juſtified of her children,</hi> my words are theſe, <hi>If there had not been a Royal ſeed of God left in every man and woman to have anſwered, owned and received the Teſtimony of the Apoſtles, they might have wandred all the World over, and have ſpent all their life time and not have gayned one convert, but there was a witneſſe for God in all,</hi> and that which lay dead did at the hearing of the voice of the Son of God live,. Here <hi>I</hi> have affirmed that there was a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for God in all, which cannot honeſtly be denyed, and <hi>I</hi> have affirmed alſo, and ſo do the Scriptures, that, that which lay dead, did at the hearing of the voice of the Son of God, live; but did <hi>I</hi> ever affirme or ſay, that the Royal Seed, the unction, the Lord of glory, and Chriſt in all lay dead, till it did at the hearing of the voice of the Son of God, live? or that Chriſt the Son of God lyeth dead, till he hear the voice of Chriſt the Son of God, and live?</p>
            <p>But it appears, thou knowes not what that was which lay dead, to which the Goſpel was preached, &amp; ſo in thy darke imagination, thou ignorantly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes thou knowes not what, and caſts a lye upon the innocent, for <hi>I</hi> never did affirme theſe things thou reporteſt of me, ſo there thou art found with a lye in thy mouth, and to be a falſe accuſer of the innocent and the confuſed nonſence and blaſphemy is turned back into thy own boſome.</p>
            <p>To that which remaines, (thy vnſavoury riming excepted) this <hi>I</hi> write that the anſwer of a good conſcience is wanting in you, notwithſtanding your imagined water baptiſme, here <hi>I</hi> ſpeak to thee and thoſe in fellowſhip with thee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and do appeal to Gods witneſſe in all your conſciences, whether your yea be yea, and your nay, nay in all things, and whether you be not in the reſpect of perſons or vain cuſtomes and faſhions of the heathen: and whether the true bridling of the tongue be witneſſed by you. As for <hi>Peter</hi> I know he baptized with outward water upon permiſſion, not by precept. And <hi>Paul</hi> did ſee that Ordinance or practice idolized in his daies and ſo laid it a ſide, ſaying, <hi>He was not ſent to baptize but to preach the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſurely if that eye in you that ſhould ſee, were not blinded, you might ſee the hand of the Lord is held forth againſt you, and that his glory is depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from you; is there nothing amiſſe among you, that the Lord thus ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters you and breakes you in peeces like a potters veſſel? let his witneſſe ſearch you, have you not loſt your firſt love? have you kept your garments pure? have you abſtained from idoles? and as for your outward water, I ſhall now ſay no more to that but this. <note place="margin">2. Kngs 18 4.</note>
               <hi>Remember the brazen ſerpent.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Written by a lover of your Souls <hi>Martin Maſon.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Lincoln.</hi> 
                  <date>28. <hi>Day</hi> 5. <hi>Moneth</hi> 1659.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
